[music]
Hello, my name is Evgeny Sokolov.
I work at the Faculty of Computer
Science at the Higher School of Economics. I teach
machine learning, head the
Big Data and Information Retrieval Department, which
means I am essentially responsible for finding
teachers for a large number of
courses that we teach, and so on. What does it
mean to study artificial intelligence?
What area of ​​knowledge does the study of
artificial intelligence and its
tools fall into? Artificial intelligence
is a very complex and perhaps not entirely
formal term. This can
mean many things: some simple
algorithms that, for example, can
predict the dismissal of an employee, and
super complex neural networks for generating
text, translating speech into text, and so on.
And depending on which side
we look at it from and what aspect we want to
know, a very different story can arise here.
For example, you can study the
mathematics of artificial
intelligence in general. What mathematical methods and
mathematical technologies are behind
all this? For example, we have a master's
program called the mathematics of
machine learning, in which, in fact, all this
happens. You can study the
methods themselves, how these neural networks are
structured, for example, then this is an area of
computer science in which there are
Mathematics and programming But this is still
computer science. But you can, for
example, study the engineering aspects of
artificial intelligence, such as
making it all work on a
phone. How can we make it so that we can
train neural networks on thousands and
maybe even tens of thousands of
computers? Then this is more like software
engineering. Software engineering is
also a section of computer science, but
completely different. In general, there is a very
large field here. What skills and
competencies need to be developed to become a
specialist in the field of artificial
intelligence. Well, I would say that there are
three areas in which you need to
pump up. The first is still
mathematics, because the methods of
artificial intelligence are somehow
impossible to understand if you do not understand
at least the basics of mathematical
analysis, linear algebra,
probability theory, mathematical statistics. I'm
not saying that you need to become an expert in
this field, that you need to be able to prove
new theorems, no, but at least gain
intuition about matrices, matrix
decompositions, derivatives. Well, without this, you can't go
anywhere. If you don't understand this, you will not
be able to master the new methods of
artificial intelligence that
arise constantly. The second, of course, is
necessary.  learn to program
Because now, of course, a lot is said about the
development of No CDE or as they call
Zero Code tools that allow you to
build some kind of algorithm without writing a
single line of code. These are still very
limited in their capabilities,
tools that basically need to program
in Python or other convenient languages.
Well, and thirdly, you actually need to study
artificial intelligence, you need to study
all the varieties of models that are
used there, and I will note that although today
we often hear in the news about neural
networks, artificial intelligence is far from
only neural networks, there are also
classical methods that sometimes turn out to be very
powerful, you need to understand
this, you need to get experience working with
data collection data. Because if there is no
data, if there are no examples of solving the problem,
then it will not work to build the same
neural network. Well, in general, all this
needs to be done, and in fact, I have
now told only a small
part of all the diversity that
exists around artificial intelligence.
What career prospects and
advantages do knowledge and skills in
the field of artificial intelligence open up? I would
divide it into two parts. The first is the
situation when you want to become a
specialist practicing in the field of
artificial intelligence, and the second is when
you want to enrich your  competencies in
some other field, knowledge of
artificial intelligence methods. If we're
talking about the first thing, to be a
specialist, there's certainly a
huge demand for such people today.
Yes, of course, we hear a lot about
generative models, neural networks, and the
use of artificial intelligence in a
variety of industries. It's expensive
to buy equipment there, and it's difficult
to collect data there. But the biggest shortage is
in people who can
do this, who can build these algorithms. The
second is the application of
artificial intelligence in a specific
profession. Well, for example, take
marketing today. Marketing is completely
different. We have the Internet, we have
so much data that there is the
possibility of very deep
personalization. When we can build
algorithms that, for each
user, based on all the data
we know about him, will
recommend him what to buy, what to
watch, what to listen to, where to go for
dinner, and so on. Of course, a marketer
won't build these algorithms from scratch.
Firstly, he must be a competent
customer who will correctly explain to
a specialist in artificial intelligence in
machine learning. What needs to be
optimized, what metrics, and what is a
good solution? What is a bad solution? How will
errors in recommendation systems be
recalculated into some of our own?
economic losses and all this a
marketer should be able to explain. But how
can he explain it if he does not understand
how it all works? If previously,
for example, the success of an advertising campaign could be
measured only by whether
our product sells well or not, today there
are much better
analytics tools. We can calculate different
metrics based on the results of an advertising campaign. We
can conduct AB tests when we
try on different audiences, for example,
advertising texts, different options for discounts,
offers, and so on. This
needs to be correctly calculated. A team of
programmers and specialists in
artificial intelligence is needed to
do all this. And this, of course,
opens up huge prospects. I
can say from my experience that if a
person who is, for example, a marketer,
designer, manager, and so on,
has basic skills in analytics,
EU programming, if he understands how the
same neural networks are structured, this makes him
simply invaluable. This really radically
increases his importance in the labor market.
Where and how would you advise to start
studying artificial intelligence? It
seems to me that it is very important here to
move on to practice as quickly as possible. Well, that is, for
example, if we are talking about
programming, there is no need to buy
any fundamental works on languages
You will
very quickly lose it if you start
reading this. It is better to take online courses. For
example, HSE has a wonderful
online course on Python. There
are practical exercises right after the first videos.
Where you can
try writing code and find out whether
you wrote it correctly or not. It is
important to look for courses that provide
quick feedback. Where you
can quickly move on to
trying to do something yourself.
Then you will not lose motivation. If we
are talking about mathematics, then everything is, of course, more
complicated. You can try taking the
same online courses in mathematics. But this
can be more difficult because,
firstly, many of us have been instilled with an
aversion to mathematics at school. There is a feeling
that it is something insanely difficult. In
fact, this is not the case. And in general,
feedback from a live
teacher is much more important. Therefore, if we
are talking about such a fundamental
study, it is more correct to consider
additional education courses or
full-fledged master's degrees. It is great if you do
not just follow the
curriculum but also try something yourself. A
very popular topic is
analysis competitions.  There are many different
platforms on the Internet where you can find data. A
company posts a task,
provides data for it, formulates
quality criteria, and you can participate. I'm
certainly not urging you to win
such competitions, especially
popular ones. It's a lot of hard work, but
just participating and trying to take a place.
Well, reading some discussions
can give a very serious boost to
development in this area. You can try to
do some kind of ped project. For example,
you have an idea that you could, say,
from a video from a camera that you have at home,
understand what your code is currently doing.
While you're away, you can
also try to figure out how to get footage from the camera.
How to build a model that
understands what the cat is doing. For this, you'll
probably have to collect data. How to
collect it, even if in the end you don't
succeed, you'll gain invaluable
experience when you encounter
real-world problems and think about how to
solve them. This will definitely be very useful to you
in your work. Yes, and even at an interview, if you
talk about such attempts, it will be a
definite plus. What
educational programs exist related to
the capabilities of artificial intelligence,
what can be learned from them, and what to expect from them.
Well, here we are talking  about online
programs and those that I want to
tell you about six of them. The first is the
online bachelor's degree in computer science and
data analysis at our faculty. This is
fundamental training. Well, it is clear that the
bachelor's program is 4 years where you
will fully study mathematics,
programming, and algorithms, and one of the
specializations in this program is
dedicated to machine learning. Where you will
fully study these methods of
deep machine learning and become a good
specialist in artificial intelligence,
but it is clear that the bachelor's degree is not for
everyone; it is a serious commitment to study for 4 years,
so let's move on to the master's degree.
This is, of course, a master's degree called
artificial intelligence, which
focuses on what is under
the hood of these methods, how they work,
there is a focus on engineering issues,
how to implement all this, how to collect data,
and so on. And this is the Master of
Data Science master's degree in English, which is also
dedicated to machine learning methods, but
focuses a little more on classical
machine learning, which is used in
many places too. And again, if we
are talking about such fundamental skills,
there is a master's degree in data engineering,
everything that happens before building
algorithms for artificial intelligence.  How
to organize data collection
How to store this data How to analyze
this data What technologies are needed here
How to control the quality of this data
how to visualize it correctly and
much, much more And in this
master's program, the necessary
technologies and methods are discussed and, by the way, the demand for
Dato engineers for those who prepare data
for artificial intelligence is now
Perhaps even higher than for
specialists in creating
artificial intelligence models. We
have two master's programs that are dedicated to
the application of knowledge in certain
areas. If we talk about more general
things, then this is a master's program in
big data analytics, which is actually
dedicated to analytics, not even so much about how to
build models. But how to work with
data. For example, you have data
on sales, data on clients. They are
in the database, what to do with them? What hypotheses
can be formulated, what questions to
ask? What mathematical methods
can be used to answer these
questions, how to analyze the same AT and
online experiments? How to correctly
analyze a product, calculate certain
metrics - all this is discussed there and
it will be useful. Well, probably for everyone who
plans to enrich their career
trajectory by working with data and finally,
this is a master's program in artificial
intelligence  in marketing and
product management, which is dedicated to Well,
actually, as the title says,
the application of these methods in marketing and in
development in product creation will be
discussed there, the application of
marketing specifics,
product specifics and how these
models can be applied, what will
happen to the labor market in connection with
the development of artificial
intelligence capabilities. Will new
professions and positions appear? It seems to me that the
demand for data taggers will definitely grow.
Well, they are also called
artificial intelligence trainers today, or
other names are invented by assessors, these are
people who actually tag the data.
For example, as I said, if we want to
make a neural network that recognizes
age from a photograph, we need to collect
data where there are photographs, there is the age of
people. Well, okay, okay, probably
people are not needed here. This can be obtained from social networks,
and so on. But what if we want,
for example, a model that
understands exactly where a face is located from a photograph?
Here we need to seat people who
will take lots and lots of photographs with people. I will
circle in squares the area where the
face is located. If we are
talking about assistants like the same
Yandex GPS gacha, then we, of course, need
very high-quality examples.  dialogues, that
is, examples of what such a question
could be. This is how it should be answered,
and these examples should cover all
areas from which
questions from users can come. This is a gigantic amount of
work, so of course, the demand for such
people will grow. I think that this is true,
at some point it can be called a
full-fledged new profession. In my
opinion, at our Faculty of
Computer Science, almost all
students now use generative
models when they write code, and I'm not
saying that they use this
only for homework, no, and then
at work in real practice, they also
use it. What will this lead to? It will become
easier to do such routine
programming. These will change, they will
remain, but simply in order to be
good specialists, you will need to master the
tools of artificial intelligence,
and thanks to them, there will be more
time for really important questions. Are
educational programs adapting to these changes and how exactly? Yes,
of course, what we do at the HSE. I will
give several examples. We have been
teaching students in most programs
digital literacy for a long time, that is, how to
be, roughly speaking, an experienced
computer user. Of course, now we will include sections dedicated to these
digital literacy courses.
Artificial intelligence tools
How to write correctly MTY generative
models What dangers are hidden in
generative models here, of course, we will
adapt, but I repeat, not all
programs need to teach this further, here is the
second example. We are well aware that
when students do their diploma theses,
they use
generative models, we do
not prohibit this in any way, and moreover, this
year we will hold a competition on the
use of artificial intelligence in
final qualification works, and I
will note that it is not necessarily that
the student used generative models to
write the text, it is possible, of course, but
this does not always work well, and
moreover, it is unlikely that a student will be able to
force a generative model to write the
substantive part for him and come up with a
solution for him, but maybe the
student also used such models to
find flaws in his research in
order to generate some hypotheses faster,
and so we will find out about this and
give awards to the best. What technologies in the
field of artificial intelligence are now
at the peak of development. I would certainly
say that today everyone is very closely
following the development of generative models,
these are large language models, dialog
assistants that  They answer our
questions with text, these are models that
generate sound, that is, they can
translate text into sound or maybe
immediately generate sound or a song in
some form, these are models that
generate video and so on. In
fact, we are in many ways only at the
beginning of the path, there is a huge number of
questions, for example, related to the same
hallucinations of these models. When they
can give out some nonsense, they can
give out incorrect facts, they can
draw unrealistic pictures or
give out some implausible video that does
not correspond, for example, to the physics of the
real world, so I would not say
that we are at the peak of development, but
Progress there is very fast, we are
quite good at solving more
classical problems. If we are talking about
understanding something from the text, what
topic it relates to, for example, to understand
something from a picture if there is a person,
say, the same recommender systems
that offer
something to the user, the methods are already very well known, it is
known How to prepare data, how
to measure quality, that is, there are already,
of course, not such boxed solutions, but there
is a very good understanding of how to approach such
problems. It is less
interesting to be there from a research point of view. But
more  It's interesting from the implementation point of view.
But generative models are
not always about implementation, but there are a
lot of open questions and it's terribly
interesting to work on this. How
artificial intelligence technologies
are used in advertising, marketing and
design. How effective this tool is
for the creative sphere is
already absolutely clear today. And it has been
clear for the last 5-7 years that analytics and artificial intelligence methods
can and should be used in marketing, and the
applications are very, very
different. This can be simply an analysis of
customer data in order to put forward
new hypotheses about what they need, what
their pain points are, and so on. Actually,
analytics should be developed and developed there, and also the
use of models that
recommend something to clients, models
that predict the effect of
certain advertising campaigns, models that,
for example, identify some strange
behavior of clients so that we can
find scammers, and so on. This is also
very actively used. Yes. And in fact,
in general, if we talk about
online advertising, any advertising on the
Internet that chooses for the user
which banner to show, which
text line to show, they are simply
stuffed with artificial
intelligence algorithms that solve a variety of
subtasks and in  Ultimately, this all boils down to a
verdict on what we show to this user,
that is, it is very, very
closely applied there, of course. Where would we be without
generative models today? A lot of
experiments are being conducted on how to
use generative models to
generate advertising texts that are
more effective, to study in general
which ads work better or worse, to
draw more
personalization. I once heard from
designer friends that they use
generative neural networks to generate
some hypotheses, throw in a
bunch of requests, get many options and,
simply inspired by this, draw
some final result.
Tools appear that simplify the
work of designers in one form or another, help there
to combine images somehow, and so on.
How to start implementing artificial
intelligence in the field of your professional
activity, be it design or
analytics, here it is important, firstly, to
understand how it works.
Because if you really understand how
generative models work. If you are
proficient in classical
machine learning methods, then you will be very
well aware of the
limitations of these tools. You
will understand that these are not some kind of all-
powerful machines that can solve
any given problem.  Of course not.
This is a very specialized tool
and understanding their background, you will be able to already
at the initial stages note some
inadequate ideas for their application. Well,
then you need to experiment and more. It would be
nice to have an eye for detail, it is
important to study cases from other areas
where, for example, high-tech
companies use this in their tasks,
where it is used in other industries and
maybe Looking at
areas that seem completely irrelevant to you, a
spark will flash through you, you will see that this is exactly it.
Here is something similar. You can
ingratiate yourself with artificial intelligence
completely different methods, however, those
mental skills that you  Get it
when you understand the current
state of artificial intelligence will
certainly help you to stay up to date
with everything new that is
being invented and that is how you will
always be in the flow. Don't be afraid
to invest in your education. Don't
be afraid to acquire fundamental skills,
so we are waiting for you in our programs where
we will definitely teach you everything
[music]
this and